《斯巴达克斯：血与沙》
《旧伤》
和曾经亲爱的朋友
It is never an easy thing to see
天人永隔
a friend once loved
真让人难过
now absent breath.
他不该死的
He should yet walk.
他应该傻傻地笑着
That foolish grin,
继续做着自由之梦
and dreams of a life beyond these walls.
天一破晓
Every night breaks.
我们就得醒来
And we must all wake.
真希望天神能让时光回溯…
I would the gods turn back the sun…
让我回到他的身边
and set me in his place.
他为荣耀而战
He fought with honor.
正如你一样
As did you both.
只为了博孩子欢心 就让他命丧黄泉
His heart was stilled for a boy's amusement.
有何荣耀可言？
Where is the honor in that?
Varro是作为角斗士 离开尘世的
Varro left this world a gladiator.
也将作为角斗士 被人怀念
And shall be remembered as such.
不
No.
他将作为一名丈夫
He will be remembered as a husband.
一位父亲
A father.
以及共同抗敌的盟友 被人怀念
And a friend amongst enemies.
Aurelia啊…
Aurelia…
这是真的吗？
Is it true?
他死在你的剑下？
That he perished by your sword?
他敬你如兄长啊
He loved you as a brother.
他受不了这个打击
He's not going to take this loss well.
谁又能怪他呢？
And who can fucking blame him?
Calavius轻飘飘一句话 就杀了我的人
Calavius slaughters my stock at the whim of his maggot,
唾弃我的雄心壮志
shits upon my ambitions,
让我在自己的地盘受辱
mocking me in my own house.
不 这绝不是受不受得了打击的问题
No, not a loss to be taken fucking well.
我迟早要以牙还牙
But one that will be answered in kind.
出去
Out.
他是行政官
He is a magistrate.
跟他作对…
To move against him…
他不过是个普通人
He is but a man.
只是所有人
And all men fall,
都对他们俯首帖耳而已
beneath the heel of their hubris.
Quintus啊…
Quintus…
这事先暂搁一边
Turn thoughts toward other matters.
Ilithyia怎样了？
What of Ilithyia?
她说动他丈夫 对我们进行资助了么？
Does she move to secure us her husband's patronage?
她已经前去罗马见Glaber了
She has departed for Rome to meet Glaber.
好消息啊
Welcome news.
有了副将的支持
The support of a legatus
要掌握政权 将指日可待
should be more than enough to gain political office.
真遗憾 Calavius有生之年
I only regret Calavius
见不到Batiatus这个「卑微」的名字
will not live to see the "unworthy" name
平步青云了
of Batiatus so elevated.
这个想法…
The very thought of discovery…
真让人不安
It turns the stomach.
我意已决 等着瞧吧
Make it a thing of iron, and see it settled.
有什么消息？
What news?
说吧 别让我失望
Speak, caress my ear with words.
绝对会让您心神愉悦的
You will find them soft and pleasing.
我们在行政官
We set upon the magistrate
离城的路上 袭击了他
on the road leaving the city.
守卫和马车呢？
The guards and wagon?
都安置妥当了
Attended to as instructed.
那个人
The man himself removed
已到了指定地点
to the appointed place.
Ashur呢？
Ashur?
在放哨
Standing watch.
夜幕降临后 我会接替他
I will relieve him by cover of night.
我会过去看看的
I shall accompany.
我要盯着他的双眼
I would gaze into the man's eyes,
看它们在我的淫威之下 是如何一番神色
and see the power of my reflection in them.
完事后 我再答谢你
Until such time, avail yourself of my hospitality.
美酒 佳人…
Wine, women…
一样也不能少
Both would suit me.
理所当然
And so deserved.
主人 告辞
Dominus.
木已成舟？
It's done, then?
没
No.
才刚开个头而已
It's only just begun.
看啊 这就是骁勇的卡普亚战神
Behold, the glorious champion of Capua.
他有心事 自然力不从心
A heavy heart weighs a man's sword.
兄弟的过世 令每位角斗士都很伤感
The loss of a brother is heartfelt by every gladiator.
但我们不应以眼泪来怀念他
We honor him not with tears,
而应当代之以 竞技场上血染的风采
but with blood spilled in the arena.
这话才像是一位真正的战神该说的
Spoken as a true champion.
和庞贝城的角斗赛即将来临
The games against Pompeii approach.
之前 我败给了Solonius的终极勇士
Years I have been robbed of the primus
和他的不择手段
by Solonius and his bribes.
最后 是我们的主人救了我
Finally it is secured by our Dominus.
那么 会派谁上场呢？
And who fights?
斯巴达克斯
Spartacus.
伤心的小娘儿们
The woman who grieves.
斯巴达克斯
Spartacus.
主人传召你
You are summoned.
这真的像我吗？
Is this truly my likeness?
随着岁月流逝
Have so many years passed,
这块石雕 是否也会刻上满脸皱纹？
that marble must be etched with such lines?
每个活着的人 都会看到自己的脸渐渐衰老
Would that every man lived to see his face so marred.
光滑的皮肤渐渐布满皱纹
And the wretched pass smooth of skin.
Varro的死 一直在我脑海中盘旋
Varro's death has been foremost in my thoughts.
损失了这么一员大将
It seizes the breast
我心痛如绞
to lose a gladiator of such standing.
这个比喻不恰当
The comparison is false,
对于儿子来说 他失去的是父亲
to a son losing his father.
对于妻子来说 她失去的是丈夫
A wife, her husband.
今后肯定会很艰难吧
A burden, to be sure.
尽管他知道危险
Yet he was aware of risk
还是自愿甘之如饴
and took them of his free will.
他是一名角斗士
As a gladiator.
不是小孩在玩过家家
Not a child's plaything.
行政官和他儿子 让我们如此痛苦
The magistrate and his whelp have caused us both pain.
我答应你 这事绝不会就这么不了了之的
It will not go unanswered, I promise you.
我会让他们付出代价的
I would be of service towards the deed.
希望这个消息能让你好过些
Take comfort from knowing its intent.
我打算让你参加
I would have your focus turned towards
庞贝城的竞技赛
the games of Pompeii.
那个混蛋Solonius
That perfumed shit Solonius
总是靠着溜须拍马 让自己保有终极勇士的名额
always secured the primus by inserting tongue in ass,
没想到 竟会被本城其最讨厌的对手击败
Only to be crushed by our city's hated rival.
但今年
But this year
他失宠了
he falls out of favor.
今年 Batiatus家族
This year the house of Batiatus
将捍卫荣誉！
secures the honor!
斯巴达克斯
Spartacus,
送雨的使者 将对阵Pericles
Bringer of rain, to face Pericles,
庞贝城的巨人！
Titan of Pompeii!
这是一场终极决斗？
It is to be sine missione?
不谈宽恕 不讲仁慈
No quarter given, no mercy shown.
钱呢？
And the purse?
按竞技赛的标准计算
To be on a footing with the match itself.
我希望能付给Varro的妻子
I would see it paid to Varro's wife.
赢得的巨款
A substantial sum.
你是说 全部都给她？
You would see it all past from your fingers?
连同日后我在竞技场上赢到的所有钱 都给她
Along with future winnings that I claim in the arena.
真大度
A noble gesture.
我也会照做的
One I shall see matched.
你也会这样做？
You would do this?
为了Varro？
For Varro?
我是为你这样做的 斯巴达克斯
I would do it for you, Spartacus.
知道他的家人有人照料
That you have peace of mind,
你就能安心了
knowing his family is attended to.
这些伤心事 对你明显影响巨大
These sad events have obviously taken their toll.
好好休息 务必对那些
Rest, and be reassured that those responsible
使我们痛苦的人 还以颜色
for our pain will soon drink deep of their own.
Varro的事 我很遗憾
It is regretful, what happened to Varro.
我看到你的眼神 知道你有多想
I saw in your eyes how you craved to
违抗命令 不杀他
defy order of his death.
但你没这样做 真可耻啊
A shame you did not attempt it.
混蛋！
Goat-fuck!
早就知道会这样！
I knew it!
那你还废话什么？
Why do you fucking bleat?
你和我并肩作战呢 兄弟！
You fight by my side, brother!
就像连体婴一样
Like a suckling babe.
我想证明自己的实力
I would prove myself alone.
该死
And die the same.
我们的战神 看起来精神不振啊
Our champion does not look to form.
嗯 天神惩罚了他
Hm, the gods punish him.
所为何事？
For what offense?
你装糊涂呢吧
You fucking jest.
Varro的鲜血
Varro's blood,
还令他的手为之刺痛呢？
still wet upon his hands?
他是迫不得已 听令行事的
His hands were removed from choice.
若是要我杀了自己的兄弟 我宁愿先死一步…
I would die before I would kill my own brother…
那么 谁来照顾你兄弟的家人？
And who would see to your brother's family?
你会怎么办 Duro？
What answer do you give, Duro?
你们俩都死了的话
With both of you dead,
谁来照顾他妻子？！
who would see to his wife?!
还有他的孩子？！
His child?!
我的兄弟没有妻儿
My brother has no wife or child.
等等！
Wait!
该死的色雷斯人
Fucking Thracians.
抱歉
Apologies.
我刚刚叫你…
I called your name…
我没听到
I did not hear.
真不像平时的你
You do not appear yourself.
是主人派你来的？
Did Dominus send you?
他希望看到你振作起来
He would see your spirits raised.
他们不配
They do not deserve it.
斯巴达克斯…
Spartacus…
你的伤口…
Your wound…
只是道擦伤
It's a scratch.
Varro比我惨多了
Varro suffered worse.
我扶你进房
I will help you to your cell.
不必
You are not needed.
抱歉
Apologies.
Mira啊
Mira.
我看见 那个和你在一起的男人…
The man I saw you with…
是主人派我去服侍他的
I was ordered to tend to his needs.
我对他没那个意思
He means nothing to me.
我不是说这事
Such is not my concern.
他是为了保护我妻子 才受伤的
The man was wounded trying to protect my wife.
下次 你和他在一起的时候
Next you lay with him,
请代我转达谢意
I would have you offer my gratitude.
Batiatus啊…
Batiatus…
委屈您屈居陋室了 行政官
Apologies for the accommodation, Magistrate.
请放心
Take comfort knowing that you will not
您不必忍耐太久
have to endure for long.
你是不是疯了？
What is this madness?
疯了？
Madness?
不
No.
我理智得很
It's only reason,
受伤至深 惟出此下策
born of a clear mind and wounded heart.
受伤？
Wounded?
我从未伤害过你
I have done you no injury.
这人伤了别人 却完全不自知
The man's crimes escape his lofty notice.
放开我！
Release me!
我也想的
Oh, I intend to.
使你从这世上解脱
From this fucking world.
不管你有何意见
Whatever your disagreement,
我们来心平气和地谈谈
let us discuss it as civilized men.
不 你搞错人了吧
No, you mistake me.
我身份卑微
I am but a base animal.
只是个受歧视的下贱人
A beast to be ridden and disregarded.
Batiatus啊…
Batiatus…
你接受了我的热情款待
You accept my hospitality.
进了我家
Enter my home.
吃了我的食物 喝了我的酒
Break bread, drink my wine.
却当面唾弃我
Only to spit in my face.
「把政治留给那些为此而生的人们」
"Leave politics to the men who have the breeding for it."
我无意冒犯
Offense was not my intent.
我只想使你免于蒙受更多的耻辱
I sought only to spare you further humiliation…
还是为我好？！
Spare me?!
你为我好个屁
You don't have power to spare shit,
你这贱人！
you pathetic cunt!
呃！
Uh!
现在说啊！
Now speak the words!
说说我家怎么样！
Tell me my heritage!
说我的家族如今已在
Tell me my family name bears no weight
你和那些傻逼眼中一文不值！
among you and your noble cock eaters!
呃？
Huh?
说啊！
Speak!
抱歉 主人
Apologies, Dominus.
脚下留情吧…
Perhaps if you move your foot…
把他抬起来
Lift him up.
是 主人
Dominus.
你想听我说话？
You wish words from me?
给我好好听着
May you listen to them well.
你太可笑了
You are a jest.
曾经低声下气的
A man tolerated,
就因为拥有斯巴达克斯这张王牌
because of his ownership of Spartacus,
卡普亚的救世主
the savior of Capua.
他倒下之日
When he falls,
就是你灭亡之时
you will quickly follow.
在这种破地儿里 拴在椅子上
Tied to a fucking chair in the filth and mire,
还这么猖狂！
and yet the man provokes!
你还不明白吗 Batiatus？
You still do not see it, do you, good Batiatus?
与你相比 我位高权重
You are beneath me.
你不管是在哪辈子
And you always will be,
都拼不过我
in this life or the next.
哎呀 伤你自尊了 快安慰自己去吧
Do what you must to balm your wounded pride.
我不会求你的
I will not beg.
求我？
Beg?
不 你早就没权力求我了
No, the time for begging is long past.
我们已经制定好周密计划
Plans have been set in motion.
为了你… 和年轻的Numerius
For you… and young Numerius.
与我儿子有何关联？
What does my boy to do with it?
他现在成年了
He is a man now.
也该粉墨登场了
He too has a part to play in our little drama.
Batiatus 你…
Batiatus, you…
看着点他 别出差错
Attend he does not injure himself.
到点时 我再来见他
I would see him fresh for the appointed time.
这样好吗 主人？
Is this wise, Dominus?
我们如果…
Perhaps if we err…
啊！
Argh!
少废话 按计划说的做
Take hold of your cock and follow the plan, uh.
我们已登上贼船
We are committed,
下不来了
we are committed.
知道了 主人
Dominus.
竞技赛快开始了！
The games approach!
击败庞贝城的角斗士
Prove yourselves against Pompeii,
为Batiatus家族争光！
and honor the house of Batiatus!
我兄弟无意冒犯
My brother meant nothing by his remarks.
他是个直肠子
He spoke his mind.
谁都知道他有话直说
Thoughts shared by many.
你想休息了？
You wish to rest?
我想休息时 会告诉你的
If I do, I shall tell you.
我伤到你了吗…
Did I hurt you…
战神？
Champion?
快去疗伤吧
Tend to the wound.
斯巴达克斯！
Spartacus!
斯巴达克斯…
Spartacus…
这人都半死不活了！
The man is half dead!
你他妈的就没注意到吗？！
You didn't notice he needed fucking attention?!
我还以为 他就是为Varro的死有点失神
I thought him only distracted by Varro's death.
他还能与庞贝城的角斗士一战吗？
Will he be able to fight against Pompeii?
他发高烧呢
He burns with fever.
能捱到比赛前就是奇迹了
A miracle if he lives to the games.
给我份所需药物的清单
Provide a list of all that is needed.
Ashur去集市了 他会搞定的
Ashur heads to market, he will see it filled.
从现在开始 悉心照料他
Let not a moment pass with him unattended.
若需要帮手
Fetch Mira from the villa
就去庄园把Mira找来
if you need assistance.
他好像有点喜欢那女孩
He has some feelings towards the girl.
她在旁照料 有助于他康复
Her touch may aid recovery.
我们的战神不能倒下
Our champion can not fall.
是 主人
Dominus.
跟庞贝城的终级勇士之战 终于快到了
The primus against Pompeii finally mine
结果老天却这么整我！
and the gods jam cock in ass!
如果斯巴达克斯不出战
The crowd will turn upon me when they
民众会骂死我！
learn Spartacus does not fight!
也许合适的替代者 可以平息民怨
Perhaps they will be appeased with suitable replacement.
除了斯巴达克斯 还有谁能击败他们那该死的战神？
Who but Spartacus could best their fucking champion?
确实有一个人…
There is but one…
终级勇士？
The primus?
是我的了！
Mine!
Batiatus终于想起了我的价值
At last Batiatus remembers my worth
而我将重返竞技场
and I shall take the sand again.
我要让竞技场的黄沙 被Pericles的鲜血染红！
And see it turn red with the blood of Pericles!
小点声啊
Soften your words.
我们会被发现的
We will be discovered.
他们爱听就听呗
Will let them hear us.
今晚 我就是神！
Tonight, I am a god!
我将夺回我的称号
And I will reclaim my title,
卡普亚战神…
champion of Capua…
你听了好像不太开心啊
The news does not please you.
只要看到你还活着 我就已经很开心了
It fills my heart with joy, to see you so alive.
我不想看到你去冒险
And would have you remain so.
Naevia啊…
Naevia…
跟终极勇士的比赛 可是会要命的啊 Crixus
The primus is a fight to the death, Crixus.
你已经好几月没进过竞技场了
You have been absent the arena many months.
如果Pericles是…
If Pericles were…
嘘
Shh.
他不会的
He will not.
你怎么能肯定呢？
How can you be certain?
因为我永远都不会离开你的
Because I will never leave your side.
就算死神想把我们分开 他也会怕得发抖
Death itself will tremble if it tries to part us.
明天 在我胜利之后
Tomorrow when I take victory,
我会向上席的你 投去注视
I will look to you in the pulvinus.
我们俩好好分享胜利时刻
We will share the moment alone.
钱已经到手了
Your hand is weighted.
该付诸行动了吧
Now float your tongue.
你安全了
You are safe.
我的主人有更大的事情
My master has greater concerns
需要他去操心
requiring his attentions.
是什么事 能让老Batiatus如此心烦意乱？
What plagues good Batiatus to such distraction?
你是不会了解的
Matters beyond your worries.
看来 它们也困扰着你
Yet they clearly trouble you.
放下你的顾忌 告诉我吧
Confide, lift your burden.
他已经变得不计后果
He has grown reckless.
他对权力和复仇的渴望
His thirst for power
蒙蔽了他的判断
and vengeance clouds judgment.
怎么说？
How so?
今天晚上跟你见面我可是冒了很大的风险
I have taken too great a risk meeting with you this night.
在我迟到之前
I must to the apothecary,
我必须到药店去
Before I am overdue.
很快 终有一日 Batiatus家族
One day, very soon, the house of Batiatus
会轰然倒塌
will come crashing down.
小心可别被碎石瓦砾给埋了啊
Do not find yourself buried in the rubble.
给我按住他！
Fucking hold him down!
没事了
That's right.
放松
Easy.
好啊 来瞧瞧
Well, lick my hole.
那个傻蛋还活着啊
The pig-fucker's still alive.
对主人来说 你就只是这些
This is what you are to him.
金子 用血和肉换来的金子
Gold, mined from blood and meat.
向斯巴达克斯致敬啊
All hail Spartacus.
死亡之影的屠灭者
Slayer of the shadow.
送雨的使者
Bringer of the rain.
罗马人的战神…
Champion of the Romans…
死吧！
Die!
操！
Fuck!
伟大的庞贝就这么点能耐吗？
Is that the best the great Pompeii has to offer?
我恐怕今年的比赛会让人失望了
I fear the games will be a disappointment this year.
这点饭前的小菜算不了什么
These early skirmishes count for nothing.
胜利与否 是由终极勇士决定的
It is the primus that decides the victor.
嗯 嗯
Um hum.
你的斯巴达克斯不出场
Absent your man Spartacus,
卡普亚将会再次陷入庞贝的阴影之中
Capua shall once again find itself in PompeiI's shadow.
也许Crixus能带来光芒啊
Perhaps Crixus will bring light to the matter.
Crixus 是啊
Crixus, yes.
看到这高卢人还活着…
The crowd will be amazed…
观众们会非常吃惊的
that the Gaul is still alive.
Batiatus向我们保证 他已经从伤病中恢复过来了
Batiatus assures us he's recovered from his injuries.
看到他能活下来 可真是让人惊奇啊
That he survived at all is impressive.
从没有庞贝角斗士和Theokoles交战之后 还能活下来的
No gladiator from Pompeii ever lived against Theokoles.
年轻的Numerius说得很对啊
Young Numerius cuts to the truth.
那是他从父亲那儿继承的天赋
A talent he learned from his father.
善良的Calavius会不会到场
Does good Calavius intend to grace us
让赛事增辉啊？
with his presence?
日子过得可真快
The day grows short.
他在Picentia做一些重要的事情
Critical matters of trade in Picentia.
他肯定是推迟了归程的时间
He must have been delayed upon his return.
我肯定他会很快加入我们的
I am certain he will join us presently.
Aulus啊！
Aulus!
起来 你这该死的老色鬼！
Up, you fucking goat!
主人不是花钱让你做梦
Dominus does not pay you to dream of tits
玩女人的
and cunts.
要敢再踢我
Place foot on me again,
我就让你再一次变成瘸子
and find yourself once more a cripple.
你知道我们的协议
You know the stakes we deal.
如果Calavius逃走的话…
If Calavius were to escape…
你他妈的给我闭嘴
Fuck your mouth shut.
他还没死
The man has not stirred.
但是也活不了了！
Nor does he breathe!
Batiatus有令 不到约定时刻
Batiatus commanded he not expire
他决不能断气！
until the appointed hour!
他还活着 你他妈唠叨啥
He's still alive, you fucking woman.
醒醒吧 虚荣鬼！
Raise yourself, peacock!
妈的…
Shit…
这都怪你
This is on you.
和我无关…
I will share no…
安静！
Quiet!
他有呼吸
He breathes.
他还活着
The man is still alive.
Aulus啊！
Aulus!
我要把你们两个都钉上十字架！
I will have you both crucified!
还有你们的主人…
And your master…
Aulus 够了！
Aulus, enough!
Aulus啊！
Aulus!
让我看看
Let me see.
虽然丑得想妓女的穴 但你不会死的
Ugly as a whore's gash, but you will live.
回训练场去 让医生帮你治疗下
Return to the ludus and have medicus attend to it.
你够胆一个人看守他吗？
Do you have the balls to see this through alone?
只有俩
Two of them.
不过很大
Very large.
快去吧
Go.
我们等不到头了
We wait an eternity.
为何不让我作为终极勇士登场？
Why don't I begin our primus?
群众威胁要暴动了
The crowd threatens riot.
我们等不了Calavius了
We can await Calavius no longer.
善良的Batiatus
Good Batiatus.
你能以我丈夫的名义 介绍终极勇士吗？
Would you present the primus on my husband's behalf?
呃 如果你觉得可行的话…
Well, if you think it proper…
请吧
Please.
唔！
Boo!
他妈的行政官哪去了！
Where's the fucking Magistrate!
我们按捺不住了！
We want some action!
卡普亚人民！
Capua!
我 谨代表行政官Calavius
In honor of Magistrate Calavius,
而他个人 为了你们 因事务繁忙而缺席了
who is absent attending vital business on your behalf,
有请 终极勇士对决庞贝勇士！
I present the primus against Pompeii!
斯巴达克斯！斯巴达克斯！
Spartacus! Spartacus!
是啊！
Yes!
是啊 我们都渴望见到斯巴达克斯
Yes, we all desire to see Spartacus,
踏上竞技场！
take to the sands!
但可惜的是
But sadly
今日见不到手执利刃的他了！
this day shall not see him with sword in hand!
但是仍有可喜之处！
Yet there is cause to rejoice!
这是个光荣的时刻
This is a glorious moment,
可以说是众望所归！
much anticipated!
因为今天将见证 卡普亚垂青之子之一
For it marks the return to the arena
重归竞技场…
of one of Capua's favored sons…
他就是Crixus！
Crixus!
高卢角斗士！
Murmillo!
他们都忘了我带给他们的荣耀
They have forgotten the honor that I have brought them.
那么此刻 你就要让他们知道
Then it is time you reminded them
谁才是他们真正的战神
who their true champion is.
卡普亚人民看起来并不喜欢你的决定
It appears Capua does not care for your selection.
他要面对的对手邪恶异常
He faces a most vile opponent,
发迹于庞贝洞穴之中
belched from the bowels of Pompeii.
有请Pericles！
I give you Pericles!
色雷斯角斗士！
Thraex!
Pericles啊！
Pericles!
我觉得这场比赛真是易如反掌！
I pray the match is overly brief!
我要看到他一脸横肉的笑脸变成哭脸
I would see his fat smirk removed.
下令吧
Give the command.
开始！
Begin!
哦！
Oh!
你他妈怎么搞的？
What was the fucking cause?
一条狗 很快就要被制伏了
A dog, soon to be put down.
喝吧
Drink.
闻着一股尿骚味
Smells like piss.
那是莨菪
Henbane.
让你好好休息的
It's to make you rest.
我要去吃东西 再睡上几个小时
I need food and a few hours sleep.
如果他情况好转 就立刻找我
Come for me if his condition changes.
庞贝万岁！
Pompeii!
又是一年 又一位卡普亚的「垂青之子」
Another year, another "favored son" of Capua
将被埋葬
gone to grass.
比赛还没结束
The match is not yet concluded.
血淋淋的事实
Formalities of blood.
你的人不行了
Your man is finished.
Crixus有狮子般的勇气
Crixus has the heart of a lion.
看吧！
Look!
他还能站…
He yet rises…
哦！
Oh!
Lucretia啊！
Lucretia!
主人
Domina.
让她喝点水
Give her water.
眼见手下即将被屠戮
Your wife does not feel well at the sight
你的妻子也于心不忍啊
of your man about to be slaughtered.
抱歉
Apologies.
太热了…
It's the heat…
送她回庄园
See her back to the villa.
我没事的
It will pass.
无需多言
No arguments.
我随后去找你
I will join you afterwards.
主人…
Dominus…
Crixus啊！
Crixus!
杀！杀！
Kill! Kill!
杀！
Kill!
Crixus啊！Crixus啊！
Crixus! Crixus!
Crixus啊！
Crixus!
如约回归了战斗状态！
Returned to form as promised!
神明回应了你的祷告
Your prayers have been answered.
这场闪电战极度简短
The match was overly brief.
卡普亚巨大的财富 市民们理应看到这一切
Good fortune to Capua, and all its deserving citizens.
噢 再多玩一会儿！
Oh, linger a moment!
让我们喝杯酒
Let us have a drink
重温这辉煌的时刻…
and relive this glorious day…
主人…
Dominus…
什么消息如此重要 竟然打断了
What news so important it interrupts
得意洋洋的Batiatus？
the gloating of good Batiatus?
找到了行政官的篷车
The magistrate's caravan has been discovered.
在镇子外边
On the edge of town.
他的护卫已遭杀害
His guards murdered.
我父亲呢？
What of my father?
没有发现你父亲 但是有迹象指明
He was not among them, but there are tracks,
他回到城里了
leading back to the city.
回卡普亚来了？
Back to Capua?
怎么会有人做出此等叛变之举？
Why would anyone commit such treachery?
为了勒索啊
Ransom.
这真让我担忧
This burden saddens me.
如果有我能帮得上忙的地方…
If I may be of any assistance…
感谢你的热心
Gratitude.
我们能处理妥当的
We can handle it.
我会召集我的手下协助搜寻
I will gather my men to aid in the search.
Numerius 非常欢迎你来我这里
Numerius, your presence is welcome.
不 我会让他跟在我的身边
No. I will have him by my side.
母亲
Mother.
我不会让他脱离我的视线之外
I will never let him out of my sight.
这是我的誓言
You have my oath on it.
好的
Ok.
来
Come.
我们去找寻你父亲
Let us to your father.
你传消息给我 我却像个普通奴隶般苦苦等候
You send message, yet I wait as a common slave.
抱歉
Apologies.
想要掩人耳目外出 并非易事
It was difficult to move without notice.
全城都警戒起来了
The alarm is up across the city.
有话快说
Speak quickly.
我加入了搜寻Calavius的队伍
I join the search for good Calavius.
他失踪了
He's gone missing.
我知道他不见了
I am aware of his absence.
我想说的重中之重是这个
The very matter I wish to broach.
Calavius的戒指！
Calavius' ring!
嘘！
Shhh!
小声点！小声点！
Softly! Softly!
你是怎么弄到这个的？
How did you come by this?
为了达成你的目的 只好不择手段
Through means pressing upon your desires.
Batiatus抓住了他 意图将其杀害
Batiatus holds him captive, with intent of murder.
就算是Batiatus 也不能这么疯狂啊
Madness, even for Batiatus.
行政官Calavius侮辱了他
Magistrate Calavius insults him,
阻碍了他的野心之路
obstructs his ambitions.
我还从未见过Batiatus如此丧心病狂
I've never seen Batiatus so unhinged.
我要跟他断绝关系
I would sever bonds,
免得自己跟他一样 遭灾受罚
least I find myself upon the cross beside him.
Calavius他
Calavius.
还活着吗？
Yet lives?
危在旦夕
For the briefest of moments.
他被关在哪里？
Where is he held?
喔 你嘴上说着断绝关系 实际上还是忠贞不二啊！
Oh, you speak of severing bonds, but remain firmly tethered!
我可不愿意对旧主愚忠下去
I hold no love for old loyalties,
但是Calavius看到了我的脸！
yet Calavius has seen my face!
我必须逃离这城市
I must flee this city,
还得想个好办法
and would have proper means to do so.
拿着
Take it.
当Batiatus和他的叛变
And more, when Batiatus
土崩瓦解之时 你的酬劳还会更丰厚
and his treachery are laid to rest.
来 我们必须召集人手
Come, we must gather men.
在你动手之前 Calavius可能就已经死了
Calavius would be dead before you do.
Batiatus已经着手实施计划了
Batiatus already moves towards his plan.
你有武器吗？
Are you armed?
只有一把匕首…
A simple dagger…
足够切断绳索了
Enough to cut ropes.
快！
Quickly!
机会稍纵即逝！
Or see opportunity fade!
医师？
Medicus?
Mira啊？
Mira?
为什么杀他！
Why did you kill him?
我没得选择
I had no choice.
每个人都必须接受命运的安排…
A man must accept his fate…
否则就等着被命运摧毁
Or be destroyed by it.
这就是我的命运之路吗？
Is this my path?
鲜血与死亡？
Blood and death?
上天注定你将永远
You have always been destined
给身边的人带来不幸…
for unfortunate things…
求求你…
Please…
不要再一次离开我…
Do not leave me again…
是你…
It was you…
是你 离开了我…
It was you, who left…
你务必要留心旧的伤口
You must tend to the wound.
被袭击了…
Attacked…
在路上…
On the road…
突如其来
Came out of nowhere.
留心旧的伤口
Tend to the wound.
我在这里 我在这里
I'm here. I'm here.
别动…
Be still…
不烧了
Your fevers broken.
天神真是眷顾你…
The gods have blessed you…
是的
Yes.
是很眷顾我
They have.
我去找医师
I will fetch medicus.
等等
Wait.
解开皮带
Release the straps.
我要单独和这人谈谈
I would speak to this man, alone.
目的何在？
Towards what purpose?
在走廊等我
Wait in the corridor.
如果有人过来 就大声示警
Sound warning if anyone approaches.
为了我这么做吧 Mira
Do this for me, Mira.
我会报答你的
I will be in your debt.
没有他的任何踪迹
There is no sign of him.
我父亲可能被关在任何地方
My father could be held anywhere.
他是个值得尊敬的人 很容易被认出来
He is a man of much esteem, and easily recognized.
他怎么可能不事先通知 就跑到大街上呢？
How could he be moved through the streets without notice?
我不知道
I do not know.
想一想
Think.
肯定有办法…
There must be a way…
地下水道！
The cisterns!
他们在城市之下 四通八达！
They run beneath the city and beyond!
开门！
The gates!
火把！
Torches!
Numerius 你很快就会找到父亲的
You will be with your father, soon enough.
我保证
You have my word.
你的功劳 我绝不会忘记
Your part in this shall not be forgotten.
是啊 不能忘
No, it shall not.
Calavius啊…
Calavius…
等等
Wait.
有人来了！
They approach!
我们必须抓紧时间
We must hurry.
不行 太晚了
No, it is too late.
鼓起勇气来！
Steel your fucking nerve!
我不会为你或其他任何人送命！
I will not end murder by you or any man!
想想我的一贯作风
Consider Ashur a spirit,
我连卡普亚都抛诸脑后了！
And Capua the world he left behind!
Ashur啊！
Ashur!
他们在我们上面！
They are upon us!
我必须帮你解开…
We must get you free…
Solonius 居然是你！
Solonius!
不 不…
No, no…
抓住他！
Seize him!
应该为你父亲报仇
Your father shall be avenged.
Solonius要为自己的所作所为 付出代价
Solonius will suffer for what he has done.
所有卡普亚人都会知道 你是什么破玩意儿
And all of Capua will know you for the shit you are.
你在做什么？！
What are you doing?!
告诉我事实
Tell me what happened.
快说！
Tell!
拿开你的手
Take your hands off me.
我妻子
My wife.
Sura她
Sura.
你从Neapolis带回来的奴隶
The slave you were transporting from Neapolis.
告诉我她怎么了
Tell me what happened to her.
我们在路上 被袭击了
We were attacked, on the road.
他们试图抓走她 但是…
They tried to get to her, but argh…
你的伤在哪里？
Where is your wound?
Where is the wound?
你为了救我妻子弄的那个伤口 在哪里？
You earned trying to save my wife?
警卫…
Guard…
告诉我 告诉我！
Tell me, tell me!
我只是…
I only did…
听命行事…
As commanded…
谁下令取她性命的？
Who spoke the words that took her life?
谁？！
Who?!
是Bat…ia…tus…
Bat…ia…tus…
你到底做了什么？
What have you done?
帮我把他放好
Help me restore him.
不用担心 我会负责…
You will secure my straps…
永远不要再提这件事
And never speak of this.
伤口看起来并不致命
The wound did not appear fatal.
有时候损伤并不是眼睛能看得到的
The damage was deeper than the eye could perceive.
医师说 他是被自己的血淹死的
Medicus tells he drowned in his own blood.
哦
Oh.
不错的结局
A loose end.
不必再为此忧心了
No longer needing to be tied.
嗯
Hm.
Ashur 你做得很好
You have played your part well, Ashur.
比我自己想象的 要好得多
Was greater hand than mine that conceived it.
那么容易骗过Solonius 让他相信
Solonius was easily deceived into believing
你会背叛我
you would betray me.
我知道他会相信
As I knew he would.
他绝对想不到 我是一直忠于你的
He never suspected my loyalty always lay with you.
一个不知荣耀为何物的人
A man who has no honor cannot imagine
很难理解其他人的荣耀
that trait in anyone else,
而你 拥有高于所有人的品质
and you, you have that quality above all others.
应该予以奖赏
And shall be rewarded in kind.
如您所愿 主人
Your will, Dominus.
哦 哦
Oh, oh.
天神如此眷顾Batiatus家族！
The gods truly favor the house of Batiatus!
看啊！
Behold!
斯巴达克斯死而复生了！
Spartacus risen from the dead!
斯巴达克斯！
Spartacus!
你还好吧？
You are well?
很好 主人
Yes, dominus.
我又找回自我了
I am myself again.